<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="CONTRIBUTING">
<title>How to contribute</title>
<subtitle>How you can help the ADG canvas project</subtitle>

<para>The ADG canvas is a relatively young and little project: any help
will be appreciated. This document shows a (non-exhaustive) list of
ways on how you can contribute. For any question or suggestion, fill
free to <ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/adg-devel">contact us</ulink>.</para>

<simplesect id="CONTRIBUTING.spread">
<title>Spread the word</title>

<para>The easiest way to contribute is to let the other know of the ADG
existence. Blog about it, bookmark the home page, suggest it as an
alternative to any potential user.</para>

<para>Objectively, the ADG canvas is a niche project and there is nothing
can be done about it. The target audience is a software developer
with technical design knowledge or a designer with development skills,
and I bet there are not many of them around.</para>

<para>A community, in the open source meaning, will be quite difficult to
achieve but the project itself is really innovative and there is no
other similar alternative I am aware of in the free software world.</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect id="CONTRIBUTING.reporting">
<title>Report any errors and issues or suggest new features</title>

<para>Use the <ulink url="http://dev.entidi.com/p/adg/issues/">bug tracker</ulink> to report
any bugs you find in the project while using it. The tracker is also
opened to suggestions or feature requests: just register yourself and
report whatever you fill useful.</para>

<para>If you want to be up to date with the development status or intend
to use the ADG canvas seriously, please consider joining the
<ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/adg-devel">mailing list</ulink>.
This is the main source of information where discussion about the
future of the project will take place.</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect id="CONTRIBUTING.localization">
<title>Translation of the ADG messages</title>

<para>ADG is a library so this is not a big issue. Anyway, as soon as the
<ulink url="http://dev.entidi.com/p/adg/issues/13/">gettext support</ulink> will be added,
fill free to translate it and submit the result in any way you fill
comfortable with. The procedure is pretty straight forward and the
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_gettext">wikipedia page</ulink> provides a
good introduction on the gettext usage. This section will be improved
with further details as soon as the gettext support will be added.</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect id="CONTRIBUTING.code">
<title>Patches welcome (obviously)</title>

<para>The ADG canvas is a free project (as in speech <emphasis>and</emphasis> as in beer): any
code contribution will be publicly shared. For technical details on
the way the code is implemented in the ADG project, please consult
the <ulink url="http://adg.entidi.com/api/view/HACKING.html">dedicated section</ulink>.</para>
</simplesect>
</chapter>
